Nuno Figueiredo Pires

CURRICULUM VITAE

Contact: +351 919 004 202 / nuno@nfpires.com **Birth Date:** February 26th, 1970

Address: Av Estados Unidos da América, 126 7D - 1700-180 Family: Married, 3 children

Lisboa - Portugal Nationality: Portuguese

www.linkedin.com/in/nfpires

EXECUTIVE PROFILE

Business Unit and Program Manager with responsibility for organisation, Sales/Commercial, administrative and technical coordination with Business Development, Business Plan, Strategy Definition, Innovation and Operations management, Proposals Evaluation and Contracts Negotiation, P&L, internal and outsourced team's development and coordination. Continual service improvement program implementation. Interface between technical teams, management, customers and other stakeholders.

As a leader I am Emphatic and People driven with strong focus in objectives (business and human) and organisation growth supported by Teams and People development. **Delegation**, **ownership** and **empowerment** with total **availability**, **sponsorship** and **coach attitude** are my usual tools to **grow motivation** and **targets over achievement**.

As manager I can point out a cross-sectional intervention both in the IT/IS Solutions development, delivery, operations and sales. Deep experience with Outsourcing, Multisourcing and Service Integration & Management, Service Design and Operational Management. Implementation of Agile structures and PMO's.

Complex organizations process design, implementation and management (ITIL, SOX, ISO, PMI, BSM, Agile...) with coordination of local and International audit and consulting teams. Product Owner, Scrum master coacher and Change Leader.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE (Only recent challenges)

Runtime Revolution (August 2017 – November 2017)

Portuguese Start-up. Business plan design to support a very rapid growth and three future business units kickoff.

Fujitsu Portugal (November 2016 – August 2017)

Head of Business Application Services

Function:

Europe Based Business unit management responsible to deliver all the Software and Professional Services projects in several market segments (Banking, Retail, Public Sector) in Europe, Africa and South America.

Responsibility:

- Sales management with business volume of 10M€ and assuring a growth in net sales and Gross Margin above 30%.
- Contract and Complex solution negotiation with stakeholders, business owners, customers and suppliers.

Wincor Nixdorf (September 2008 – August 2015)

Head of Software and Professional Services (Portugal, Middle East & Africa)

Function:

Leadership role with organisation responsibility from sales, software factories and international competence centres, solutions delivery with HW, SW and services integration (Consultancy, project management, technical support and partner development/enablement).

Intervention in banking and retail businesses in Portugal, Africa and Middle East with development of international projects, proposal, contracts and partnership negotiations with customers, partners and suppliers.

Reporting:

- Region Portugal & MEA reporting to the Software VP in Nederland and Regional President based in Portugal.
- Direct report: 30 engineers/PM's, 4 Business & Engagement Managers, 1 Finance Mng, 1 HR.
- Indirect Report: 5 regional business managers (Direct & Indirect sales), +700 Engineers from 65 sales and delivery partners in the region.

Responsibilities:

- Coordination of SW and Professional Services of 3 Legal Entities (Portugal, Algeria and Morocco), 3 Offices (Nigeria, South Africa and UAE), 65 partners in 73 countries.
- Teams and people hiring and development.
- Complete responsibility on solutions business development in the region.

Achievements:

Several specific solutions developed in Major Banks all over MEA Region with projects for Solutions Integration with core-banking services, branch, Self Service, Monitoring and Service Management, Mobile Money, Monitoring, multichannel/omnichannel services, Real Time Transactional Fraud identification or Currency exchange solutions, among others.

Developing the complete business model, team, processes, KPI's, methodologies and tools. In the first four years all the Division targets were overachieved (Sales Volume, Margin, Incoming Orders and EBITA) with maintenance and support contracts coverage of all customers.

Identification, selection and enablement of strategic partners with capacity to sell, develop and support complete solutions in 70 countries of MEA region.

Logica (actual CGI) / Edinfor / ITLog (2004 – 2008)

- Distributed Systems and Networking Division Manager
- World Wide Change & Release Manager

Function:

Leader with responsibilities in the EDP (Electricity of Portugal) customer, assuring the service and infrastructure operations with 800 distributed servers, 10.000 Desktops in 210 Iberia locations. +2 PetaBytes of data managed. Coordination of all the technical and business teams to deliver and develop the service.

Responsibility:

- Delivery management with the SLA's and KPI's agreement and control.
- Teams development (selection, contract, evaluation, development and technical coordination)
- Support and control processes coordination,
- Direct Report: 14 Team Leaders and 200 engineers,
- Indirect Report: Process consultants and administrative staff,

Achievements:

Implementation of the first Evaluation and Feedback process in the Division assuring that everyone in the team has agreed in a business aligned development plan with record for several coaching and mentoring activities during the year.

As World Wide Change Manager, defined the global strategy for Change and Release management. Coordination of all process owners, and Assumed the Operations in Change Management.

Security practice Team coordination with impact in the global company politics and close alignment with COBIT controls supporting SOX and ISO certification activities.

PROFESSIONAL CAREER (All challenges)

2017 – 2017	Board Member	Runtime Revolution
2016 – 2017	Head of Business Application Services	Fujitsu Services
2015 – 2016	Non-Executive Senior Strategic Advisor	Instalplus
2012 – 2015 2008 – 2015	General Manager of Portugal & MEA - SW & Professional Services Portugal Software & Professional Services Division BU Director	Wincor Nixdorf
2007 – 2008 2006 – 2008	World Wide Change & Release Manager Iberia ITIL Process Owners Teams Manager	Logica (CGI)
2004 – 2006	Distributed Systems and Networking Division Director	
2003 – 2004	Executive Manager Information Technology (6 Months)	Bright Partners
2001 – 2003	Networking business Director Euronext Lisbon Datacentre Manager	EDS (HP)
1998 – 2001	СТО	HDS
1996 – 2001	IT Manager	IST
1992 – 1996	Recital Division Leader	SuperSoft
1987 – 1992	Information Systems Team Leader	Dir Dist Finanças
1985 – 1987	Trainer BASIC Programming Language	C M Cascais

EDUCATION AND PROFESSIONAL CERTIFICATIONS

- **2000 MSc Computer Engineering** (2000), Telecommunications Branch (Thesis not presented), Instituto Superior Técnico
- 1996 BSc in Informatics (1995) and informatics Management, Instituto Politécnico Lisboa
- 1993 Bachelor's degree in Management Informatics, Instituto Politécnico Lisboa
- 2016 Certified Scrum Master Rumos
- 2016 CEH Certified Ethical Hacker EC-Council (Jan 2016)
- 2015 PMP Project Management Professional Project Management Institute (Dec 2015 PMP1882286)
- 2014 Aligning Project Management with Organizational Strategy The George Washington University
- 2011 Strategic & Conceptual Selling (Miller Heiman) Wincor Nixdorf
- 2010 Cash Cycle Mng; Technology and Sales Mng; Organizational Change Mng Wincor Nixdorf
- 2006 ITIL Foundation Certification in IT- Service Management

Other technical certifications (BMC/Remedy, HP-UX, Cisco, Alcatel, XYlan, etc)

HOBBIES

Scuba Dive (PADI Master), Sports (Fitness & BTT), aquaculture and bonsai gardening.